<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<page section="publications">
	<title><carrot-text />Publications</title>

    <chapter level="1">
        <title><carrot-text /> articles and publications</title>

        <ul>
			<li>Stanisław Osiński and Dawid Weiss: <i>A Concept-Driven Algorithm for Clustering Search Results</i>,
				EEE Intelligent Systems, May/June, 3 (vol. 20), 2005, pp. 48—54
				[in English, <a href="http://doi.ieeecomputersociety.org/10.1109/MIS.2005.38">buy the article at IEEE</a>]
			</li>

			<li>Stanisław Osiński: <i>Dimensionality Reduction Techniques for Search Results Clustering</i>,
				Master thesis, Department of Computer Science, The University of Sheffield, UK, 2004
				[in English, <a href="http://www.carrot2.org/publications/osinski04-dimensionality.pdf">PDF, 1.5MB</a>]
			</li>

			<li>Stanisław Osiński, Jerzy Stefanowski and Dawid Weiss <i>Lingo: Search Results Clustering Algorithm Based on Singular Value Decomposition</i>,
				 In: Advances in Soft Computing, Intelligent Information Processing and Web Mining, Proceedings of the International IIS: IIPWM'04 Conference, Zakopane, Poland, 2004, pp. 359—368
				[in English, <a href="http://www.carrot2.org/publications/iipwm-osinski-weiss-stefanowski-2004-lingo.pdf">PDF, 257kB</a>]
			</li>

			<li>Stanisław Osiński and Dawid Weiss <i>Carrot<sup>2</sup>: An Open Source Framework for Search Results Clustering.</i>,
				 26th European Conference on Information Retrieval (Poster session), Sunderland, United Kingdom, 2004
				[in English, <a href="http://www.carrot2.org/publications/ecir-poster-web.jpg">JPEG, 400kB</a>]
			</li>

            <li>
            Steven Schockaert: <i>Het Clusteren van Zoekresultaten met behulp van Vaagmieren
					 (Clustering of Search Results using Fuzzy Ants)</i>, Master thesis, University of 
					 Ghent, 2004,
					 [in Dutch, <a href="http://www.carrot2.org/publications/schockaert-2004-vaagmieren.pdf">PDF, 3.5MB</a>]
            </li>

            <li>
			Ngo Chi Lang: <i>A tolerance rough set approach to clustering web search results</i>,            
            Faculty of Mathematics, Informatics and Mechanics, Warsaw University, 2004,
            [in English, <a href="http://www.carrot2.org/publications/chi-lang-ngo-2004.pdf">PDF, 1.3MB</a>]
            </li>

            <li>
			Laust Rud Jensen: <i>A reuse repository with automated synonym support and cluster generation</i>,            
            Department of Computer Science at the Faculty of Science, University of Aarhus,
            Denmark, 2004,
            [in English, <a href="http://www.carrot2.org/publications/rud-2004-reuse-support-system.pdf">PDF, 1.4MB</a>]
            </li>

            <li>
                Jerzy Stefanowski and Dawid Weiss: <i>Carrot<sup>2</sup> and Language Properties in Web Search Results Clustering</i>
                In: Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence: Advances in Web Intelligence, Proceedings of the First International Atlantic Web Intelligence Conference, Madrit, Spain, 2663 (vol. —), 2003, pp. 240—249.
                [in English, <a href="http://www.carrot2.org/publications/stefanowski-weiss-awic-2003.pdf">PDF, 193kB</a>]
            </li>

            <li>
                Paweł Kowalik: <i>Wspomaganie tworzenia analizatorów stron wyników z internetowych systemów wyszukujących</i>
                (<i>Automated support for search engine wrapper induction.</i>), Master thesis,
                Poznań University of Technology, 2003,
                [in Polish, <a href="http://www.carrot2.org/publications/kowalik-2003-wrapit.pdf">PDF, 3.2MB</a>]
            </li>

            <li>
                Stanisław Osiński: <i>An Algorithm for Clustering of Web Search Results</i>, Master thesis,
                Poznań University of Technology, 2003,
                [in English, <a href="http://www.carrot2.org/publications/osinski-2003-lingo.pdf">PDF, 4.7MB</a>]
            </li>

            <li>
                Michał Wróblewski: <i>A Hierarchical WWW Pages Clustering Algorithm Based on the Vector Space Model</i>, Master thesis,
                Poznań University of Technology, 2003,
                [in English, <a href="http://www.carrot2.org/publications/wroblewski-2003-ahc.pdf">PDF, 8.5MB</a>]
            </li>

        </ul>
    </chapter>
</page>
