<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC 
    "-//Dawid Weiss//DTD DocBook V3.1-Based Extension for XML and graphics inclusion//EN" 
    "http://www.cs.put.poznan.pl/dweiss/dtd/dweiss-docbook-extensions.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % isopub SYSTEM "iso-pub.ent"> 
%isopub;
<!ENTITY % local SYSTEM "local-entities.ent">
%local;
]>

<section id="sect:installation">
    <title>Installation of &carrot;</title>

    <para>
    &carrot;'s modular architecture is very flexible, but also brings several difficult
    issues concerning its installation. Every component can be installed in a different
    web context, some of them even on physically different machines. Components must
    be configured and processes of using those components defined. While most of these
    tasks are trivial, they still require certain amount of work.
    </para>
    
    <section id="sect:inst-requirements">
        <title>Installation requirements</title>
        <!-- {{{ -->
        <para>
        The components contained in the binary distribution are written in Java and packaged as
        Web Application Archives (WAR files). A web server capable of deploying WAR archives is therefore
        required. &tomcat; is the recommended web server, although other possibilities exist like
        &jboss; or &resin;. This manual details the configuration of &tomcat; web server for use with &carrot;. 
        Installation on other containers should be similar.
        </para>
        <para>
        &java; virtual machine in at least version 1.3 is required, although version 1.4+ is recommended.
        The application should work on all vendors' JVMs, although problems have been reported in installation
        on IBM's JDK.
        </para>
        <para>
        For building the system from source code, a Java compiler (JDK) and &ant; 
        build tool are also required. 
        </para>
        <!-- }}} -->
    </section>

    <section id="sect:choosing-components">
        <title>Choosing components</title>
        <!-- {{{ -->
        <para>
        The first step is to choose components, which your &carrot; installation will use.
        Several components
        are already provided in the base &carrot; &cvs;, other may be available from independent vendors
        (we hope ;). More
        information about the available components and their locations can be found at 
        the official project website: &carrot-web;.
        </para>
        <para>
        It is important to think of the required components in terms of <emphasis>processes</emphasis> in which
        they will be linked. For example, in order to build an intranet search engine one should
        install some input component (some wrappers for existing search engines are provided in the distribution),
        a stemming filter improving the quality of clustering interface,
        LSI clustering filter for organizing search results into groups and an output component for rendering
        the result, such as xslt-renderer with an appropriate stylesheet. The result can be seen in 
        <xref linkend="figure:screenshot-lsi" />. 
        </para>
        <pasteFigure src="screenshot-lsi.png" width="5in">
        LSI clustering filter combined with other components
        </pasteFigure>
        <para>
        A good help in creating custom processes is taking a look at the templates saved directly from the &carrot;
        &cvs;. <filename>descriptors-templates</filename> folder in the distribution provides several processes
        which can serve as a basis for customization (please refer to <xref linkend="sect:modifying-descriptors"/>
        for more information about descriptor files).
        </para>
        <!-- }}} -->
    </section>

    
    <section>
        <title>Building components from sources</title>
        <para>
        In order to build Carrot2's components, you must have ANT in your path. We use 
        ANT 1.6, lower versions are not supported but may work.
        </para>

        <para>
        This command should build all the components for you and place them in tmp/dist.
        <screen>
ant build
        </screen>
        </para>
        
        <para>
        Note that the Web controller component is built with a set of component 
        descriptors for which service &url;s are hardcoded inside the descriptor
        files. To change the defaults, use the following &ant; command:
        </para>

        <screen>
ant -Ddeployment.port=80 -Ddeployment.host=myhost.com build.webcontroller
        </screen>
        <para>        
        Adjust the parameters to match your deployment configuration.
        </para>
    </section>

    
    <section>
        <title>Downloading pre-built components</title>
        <para>
        The nightly build process produces a set of <filename>WAR</filename>
        files which can be used to install &carrot; without a need to compile the
        system from source files. Please note that the controller component will
        require some manual adjustments in &url;s hardcoded in components descriptors.
        </para>
        <para>
        Nightly binaries are available at:
        <ulink url="http://carrot.cs.put.poznan.pl/static/download/nightly/" />.
        </para>
    </section>
   
    
    <section id="sect:controller-configuration">
        <title>Web controller component configuration</title>
        <!-- {{{ -->
        <para>
        The Web controller component is the glue combining other &carrot; components. The current controller
        component is a web application that mimics a search engine (although other controllers may not
        look like that at all :).
        </para>
        
        <para>
        The configuration files for the controller component can be found in <filename>controller/WEB-INF/</filename>
        folder of the distribution.
        </para>
        
        <section id="sect:cache">
            <title>Query response caches and their configuration</title>

            <!-- {{{ -->
            <para>
                <filename>cache-config.xml</filename> is a configuration file for the internal cache of the
                controller component. Caching makes sense if input components are either slow in responding to
                queries, or there are restrictions put on their use (the case with most search engines on the Web).
                Input component's response is cached for each unique combination of a query, requested number of results
                and optional parameters passed to the input component by the controller (or the process script).
                When such unique combination of attributes is requested again, the input component's response
                is simulated by the stream taken from the cache.
            </para>
            <para>
                The cache subsystem is implemented as a cascade of containers. The top-level caches should have a fast
                access (like memory-based caches), caches down the cascading chain can be slower (disk access or database
                storage). When a query is first added to cache, it is added to the top-container and descends down the
                chain if it is not reused, finally it is removed from the cache if the maximum capacity of
                the last container has been reached.
            </para>
            <para>
                Currently memory, disk and read-only caches are implemented:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                        <classname>MemoryCachedQueriesContainer</classname>
                        implements a memory cache. This can be used for fast access to recent queries, although
                        it should be kept in mind that the operating system may swap the overallocated memory
                        thus slowing it down significantly &ndash; in such case it is more reasonable
                        to add a disk cache instead.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                        An example of a memory container entry in cache configuration file is given below:
                        <informalexample id="listing:mem-cache-example">
                            <programlisting><![CDATA[@insert-file.mem-cache@]]></programlisting>
                        </informalexample>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                        <classname>ZIPCachedQueriesContainer</classname>
                        implements a disk cache. Compressed data is saved to a filesystem folder. The location
                        of the folder is given either as absolute path (<sgmltag>absolute-dir</sgmltag> element),
                        web application's context-relative path (<sgmltag>context-relative-dir</sgmltag> element)
                        or system temporary directory (<sgmltag>use-system-temp</sgmltag> set to true).
                        <emphasis>The folder must be designed for use by the cache only</emphasis> &ndash; it
                        must not contain any other files. 
                        </para>
                        <para>
                        An example of a disk container entry in cache configuration file is given below:
                        <informalexample id="listing:disk-cache-example">
                            <programlisting><![CDATA[@insert-file.disk-cache@]]></programlisting>
                        </informalexample>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                        <classname>ZIPCachedQueriesContainer</classname> can also be used in a read-only 
                        mode as a constant cache. This mode is especially useful for demonstrating certain
                        &carrot; features on precached queries.
                        Set <sgmltag>read-only</sgmltag> &xml; element to <constant>true</constant> in order
                        to prevent the cache container from saving files. Note that it makes sense to place
                        a read-only cache at the <emphasis>end</emphasis> of the caches cascade (since
                        elements will always be immediately dropped from a read-only cache.                          
                        </para>
                        <para>
                        An example of a read-only container entry in cache configuration file is given below:
                        <informalexample id="listing:ro-cache-example">
                            <programlisting><![CDATA[@insert-file.ro-cache@]]></programlisting>
                        </informalexample>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            
            <!-- }}} -->
        </section>

        <section id="sect:main-config">
            <title>Main configuration file</title>
            <!-- {{{ -->
            <para>
            <filename>carrot-config.xml</filename> is the main configuration file of the controller. It
            contains references to folders where component and process descriptors are located, name
            of the cache configuration file and other information. This section goes through the elements
            of the configuration file and describes their meaning.
            </para>
            
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>@insert-file.carrot-config@</programlisting>
                <calloutlist>
                    <callout arearefs="reloadable">
                    <para>
                        <sgmltag>reloadable</sgmltag> attribute allows the controller component to dynamically
                        reload while it is active and when the configuration file changes. This
                        attribute should be set to <constant>true</constant> only
                        during debugging or initial deployment, when component processes are often changed.
                    </para>
                    </callout>
                    <callout arearefs="components">
                    <para>
                        <sgmltag>components</sgmltag> defines a web application context-relative directory
                        where component descriptors can be found. Refer to section <xref linkend="sect:modifying-descriptors"/>
                        for more information about component descriptors.
                    </para>
                    </callout>
                    <callout arearefs="processes">
                    <para>
                        <sgmltag>processes</sgmltag> defines a web application context-relative directory
                        where process definitions can be found. Refer to section <xref linkend="sect:modifying-descriptors"/>
                        for more information about process descriptors.
                    </para>
                    </callout>
                    <callout arearefs="cache">
                    <para>
                        <sgmltag>cache</sgmltag> specifies a web application context-relative path where
                        cache configuration file can be found. This file is described in <xref linkend="sect:cache" />.
                    </para>
                    </callout>
                    <callout arearefs="guards">
                    <para>
                        <sgmltag>guards</sgmltag> specifies a web application context-relative directory where 
                        query guards definition can be found. The guards specification is defined in <xref linkend="sect:guards" />.
                    </para>
                    </callout>
                </calloutlist>
            </informalexample>
            <!-- }}} -->
        </section>
        
        <section id="sect:modifying-descriptors">
            <title>Modifying component and process descriptors</title>
            <!-- {{{ -->
            <para>
            A <glossterm>component descriptor</glossterm> is an &xml; file that provides the required information
            about the type and services provided by a component. The structure of a component descriptor file is
            defined in an &xmlschema;, which can be found in <filename>schema/component-descriptor.xsd</filename>
            file in the distribution.
            </para>
            <para>
            A detailed definition of a descriptor file can be found on the Internet at
            &carrot-web;, more specifically in chapter <citetitle pubwork="chapter">Component descriptors</citetitle>
            in the &devmanual;. The most important properties
            of a component are highligted below.
            </para>
            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>@insert-file.component-descriptor@</programlisting>
                <calloutlist>
                    <callout arearefs="component-id"><para>
                    This is the identification string assigned to the component. It is usually assigned
                    by &carrot; project maintainers and <emphasis>should not</emphasis> be changed
                    individually as it may name clash with other components. The <varname>id</varname>
                    of a component is used in process definitions and is very important.
                    </para></callout>
                    <callout arearefs="component-type"><para>
                    The type of the component. <constant>input</constant>, <constant>output</constant> or
                    <constant>filter</constant> values are possible.
                    </para></callout>
                    <callout arearefs="component-url"><para>
                    The &url; at which component's services are available to the controller. The data exchange
                    formats and specification is described in detail in the &devmanual;, and they should normally
                    be part of specification of any component. The example component descriptors in
                    <filename>descriptor-templates</filename>
                    cover the data formats accepted by the components released in the distribution.
                    </para>
                    <tip><para>
                    The &url; of a component must be available to the controller, but not necessarily to the 
                    &quot;outside world&quot;. Web application container (such as Tomcat) can be configured in such a way
                    to allow local connections (from the controller), but refuse any attempts to connect to components
                    directly.
                    </para>
                    </tip>
                    <para>
                    When deploying your &carrot; installation, modify &url; of the components replacing <replaceable>host</replaceable>
                    and <replaceable>port</replaceable> according to your individual environment.
                    </para></callout>
                    <callout arearefs="component-info"><para>
                    The information and configuration page of the component. These can (and should) be removed from
                    component descriptor in the final deployment. 
                    </para></callout>
                </calloutlist>
            </informalexample>
            
            <para>
            <glossterm>Processes</glossterm> define the way data is transformed by separate components yielding the final
            result. Process descriptor files thus specify a <emphasis>chain</emphasis> of components from the input
            through filters, to the output component. The result returned from the output component is then shown
            on user's browser (or any other devide the controller component might support).
            </para>
            <para>
            Processes can be defined in two ways: as an &xml; file or programmaticaly using scripted languages like &beanshell;
            or &javascript;. The &xml; definition is faster, but less flexible than implementing a process in &beanshell; for
            example. Below is an example of a scripted process implemented in &beanshell;. 
            </para>

            <informalexample>
                <programlisting>@insert-file.process@</programlisting>
                <calloutlist>
                    <callout arearefs="process-id"><para>
                    The identification string of a process. This string can be assigned according to one's 
                    imagination, although it must be unique within the set of processed defined for one controller.
                    Also, the <varname>id</varname> of a process is used to find its localized name in the 
                    application resources (<filename>i18n.xml</filename> file in the controller distribution).
                    </para></callout>
                    <callout arearefs="process-description"><para>
                    The default name of a process if its localized name cannot be found in application's resources.
                    </para></callout>
                    <callout arearefs="docache"><para>
                    If set to <constant>true</constant>, the controller will attempt to use cached input prior to sending requests
                    to the input component specified later on.
                    </para></callout>
                    <callout arearefs="usecache"><para>
                    If set to <constant>true</constant>, the controller component will cache the data received from
                    this process's input component.
                    </para></callout>
                    <callout arearefs="input.invoke"><para>
                    This method invokes the input component for the given query and retrieves an <classname>InputStream</classname>
                    with the results. Replace the component <varname>id</varname> to that your input component here.
                    </para></callout>
                    <callout arearefs="filter.invoke"><para>
                    This method invokes the filter component on the data stream. Here, LSI clustering component
                    is invoked with some custom parameters specified above the invocation line.
                    Replace the component <varname>id</varname> to that your filter component here (refer to 
                    examples in the distribution).
                    <tip>
                    <para>
                    More than one filter can be applied to the data stream. Just apply whatever filters sequentially to
                    the <classname>InputStream</classname> object instance.
                    </para>
                    </tip>
                    </para></callout>
                    <callout arearefs="output.invoke"><para>
                    Invokes the output component for the current data stream. Here, dynamic tree component is
                    invoked with certain customized parameters. Replace the component <varname>id</varname>
                    to that your output component here (refer to examples in the distribution).
                    </para></callout>
                    <callout arearefs="send.response"><para>
                    Sends the reponse back to the client. This method <emphasis>must</emphasis> be called
                    at the end of the process script.
                    </para></callout>
                </calloutlist>
            </informalexample>
            
            <para>
            The details of process programming 
            are beyond the limits of this guide (most often the only required change
            will be adjusting the &url;s to components in ). The best way to start is by taking a look
            at examples in the distribution.
            </para>
            
            <!-- }}} -->
        </section>

        <section id="sect:guards">
            <title>Query/ component guards</title>
            <!-- {{{ -->
            <para>
            There exist situations in which queries to a component should be limited. For example,
            some components may not be available at certain time frames, some may restrict the number
            of queries to certain limits etc. The guards describe such constraints &ndash; they are executed
            before any component is invoked by the controller. If any guard <emphasis>vetoes</emphasis>
            the access to a given component, execution of a query is stopped and the information is
            displayed to the user.
            </para>
            <para>
            Guards specification is not yet released to the public.
            </para>

            <important>
            <para>
            If any guard files are present in the official distribution of &carrot;, you must not remove
            them, disable them, or change them in any way.  
            </para>
            </important>
            <!-- }}} -->
        </section>
        <!-- }}} -->
    </section>

    <section id="sect:deploy-tomcat">
        <title>Deploying &carrot; on &tomcat;</title>
        <!-- {{{ -->
        <para>
        This section provides essential steps leading to installing &carrot; on &tomcat; web server. 
        It is assumed here that &java; (JDK) is already installed.
        </para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Download and unpack &tomcat; web server from <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/" />.
                    At the moment of writing, we suggest stable release 4.1.24.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Copy shared libraries from <filename>lib</filename> folder of the &cvs; distribution
                    to <filename>shared/lib</filename> of your tomcat installation. Alternatively,
                    you can download a ZIPped pack of shared libraries from the 
                    nightly binaries dropoff zone
                    (<ulink url="http://carrot.cs.put.poznan.pl/static/download/nightly/" />).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Build the controller component specifying the deployment host
                    and port so that component descriptors point at valid &url;s.
                    Copy the controller component to <filename>webapps</filename>
                    folder of &tomcat;.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Copy all <filename>*.war</filename> files (components) 
                    to <filename>webapps</filename> folder of your &tomcat;. The components
                    will be automatically deployed when &tomcat; is started next time.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    You may also want to configure &log4j; so that messages from &carrot; components are
                    properly saved somewhere. Create and edit <filename>conf/log4j.properties</filename>
                    in your &tomcat; installation. Type the following:
                </para>
                <informalexample><programlisting><![CDATA[# Default logging sink.
log4j.rootLogger=DEBUG,global.file

# global.file appender (/logs/carrot2.log)

log4j.appender.global.file=org.apache.log4j.FileAppender
log4j.appender.global.file.File=TRANSLATE_CONTEXT::/logs/carrot2.log
log4j.appender.global.file.Append=true
log4j.appender.global.file.layout=org.apache.log4j.PatternLayout
log4j.appender.global.file.layout.ConversionPattern=%d %-5p [%t] %c{2} -- %m%n]]></programlisting>
                </informalexample>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                <emphasis>Make sure your port number 8080 is not already taken by some other application</emphasis>. Then
                start &tomcat; using the startup script appropriate for your platform (either <filename>bin/startup.bat</filename>
                or <filename>bin/startup.sh</filename>. Wait until message <computeroutput>INFO: Starting Coyote HTTP/1.1 on port 8080</computeroutput>
                shows up on the console. This may take even a couple of minutes because WAR applications must be deployed
                and <acronym>JSP</acronym> files compiled.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                Open a web browser (&javascript; must be enabled, Internet Explorer or Mozilla is recommended) and point
                it to <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/carrot2-web-controller" />, you should see &carrot;'s query page like below.
                </para>
                <pasteFigure src="carrot-query.png" width="5in">
                Carrot web controller query page
                </pasteFigure>
                <para>
                Now follow <computeroutput>Demo</computeroutput> link on the top of the query page and select any
                of the cached preconfigured queries. A clustered result should be available within seconds (please
                allow for the components to initialize if queried for the first time).
                </para>
                <pasteFigure src="carrot-sample.png" width="5in">
                Sample demo clustered result
                </pasteFigure>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <!-- }}} -->
    </section>
    
</section>

