<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<page section="usergain">
	<title>Motivation and benefits</title>

    <chapter level="1">
        <title>What may a researcher gain from <carrot-text/>?</title>
        <p>
        A number of scientific papers concerning search results processing have been published.
        Each and every author had to go through the same tedious (and quite fruitless) tasks
        of building a search engine wrapper, incorporating stemming/ light language processing
        algorithms, and finally displaying a result of the algorithm in some form.
        </p>
        <p>
        In our opinion this is highly reduntant work and most of the components (wrappers, processing,
        displaying) can be reused. Thus, we think <carrot-text/> gives a number of possible 
        shortcuts for those willing to work with search result clustering or any other form
        of textual data processing (we envision some applications of information retrieval could also
        applied easily using the architecture we proposed):
        <ul>
            <li><b>Reusable components</b> - for a certain application, a standard data exchange
            format can be proposed, which makes components using this format replaceable and reusable.
            We proposed such data exchange format for application in search results clustering -- 
            an XML-based query and search result.
            </li>
            <li><b>Platform and language independency</b> - data transmission protocol in <carrot-text/>
            is fixed to HTTP POST. Almost any programming language can be adopted to work as a web server
            or in web-server enabled mode (via CGI for instance). This allows for true independency of
            components within the architecture -- they can be physically distributed and running
            on different hardware platforms for instance. Also, the language of implementation does not matter,
            so for research objectives slower, but more elegant languages can be used (Prolog, Lisp, Java?),
            while for production systems, if ever, the code can be rewritten for performance and the component
            reused without any changes to other parts of the system.
            </li>
            <li><b>Start your experiments fast</b> - because <carrot-text/> comes with a set of template
            component classes and utilities in Java, a researches can almost immediately set up his/ her own
            component within the framework and start working on specific thing he wants to deal with.
            </li>
            <li><b>OpenSource</b> - <carrot-text/> is an open source initiative. It is available free of charge
            and the code base can be modified to be adjusted to one's needs.
            </li>
        </ul>
        </p>
    </chapter>

    <chapter level="1">
        <title>What may a business gain from <carrot-text/>?</title>
        
        <p>
        Text clustering and especially search results clustering is a hot topic nowadays.
        <carrot-text/> provides a production-ready infrastructure and quality for such applications
        at the very convenient legal terms of the BSD license. 
        </p>
        
        <p>
        We are very proud of our open source offering -- it meets the industry standards
        concerning code quality and stability. If 
        additional performance or tuning expertise is needed, a spin-off company <a href="http://www.carrot-search.com">Carrot
        Search</a> provides both (a commercial clustering component seamlessly integrating with the open source framework
        and consulting/ tuning services).
        </p>
    </chapter>
</page>