<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN"
                 "http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % local SYSTEM "local-entities.ent">
  <!ENTITY % custom SYSTEM "custom-entities.ent">
  %local;
  %custom;
]>
<chapter xml:id="chapter.introduction" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <subtitle>What is &C2; and what it is not</subtitle>

  <para>
    &C2; is a library and a set of supporting applications you can use to build
    a search results clustering engine. Such an engine will <emphasis
    role="bold">organize your search results into topics</emphasis>, fully
    automatically and without external kowledge such as taxonomies or
    preclassified content.
  </para>

  <para>
    &C2; contains components for fetching search results from several search
    engines, such as Yahoo!, MSN Live, Google, but it also supports other
    sources of documents like Lucene, Solr or Google Desktop index. &C2;
    contains also two document clustering algorighms designed specifically for
    search results clustering: Suffix Tree Clustering and Lingo.
  </para>

  <para>
    &C2; <emphasis role="bold">is not a search engine</emphasis> itself, it
    does not have a crawler and indexer. There is a number of Open Source projects
    you can use to crawl (Nutch), index and search (Lucene, Solr) your content, which
    can then be queried and clustered by &C2;
  </para>

  <para>
    In most cases your workflow with &C2; would be the following:
  </para>
  
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Use <link linkend="section.workbench">&DCW;</link> and possibly other applications from &C2; application suite
        to see what the clustering results are like for your content.  If the
        results are promising, you can use the &DCW; to further tune the
        clustering algorithm's settings.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        If developing Java software, use &C2; API and JAR to integrate
        clustering into your code.  For non-Java environments, set-up the <link linkend="section.dcs">&DCS;</link>
        and call &C2; clustering using the REST protocol.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>
    <xref linkend="chapter.application-suite" /> of this manual introduces
    applications available in &C2; distribution. <xref
    linkend="chapter.getting-started" /> shows how to quickly set up &C2; to
    cluster your own data. <xref linkend="chapter.architecture" /> discusses
    &C2; architecture and internals, while <xref linkend="chapter.components"
    /> is an in-depth reference of &C2; components.
  </para>
</chapter>
