<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN"
                 "http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % local SYSTEM "local-entities.ent">
  <!ENTITY % custom SYSTEM "custom-entities.ent">
  %local;
  %custom;
]>
<chapter xml:id="chapter.lexical-resources" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Lexical resources</title>
  <subtitle>Stemming, tuning common words and filtering cluster labels</subtitle>

  <para>
    &C2; will attempt to perform clustering of any textual content, regardless
    of the actual language the content is written in. However, certain level of
    shallow linguistic preprocessing usually helps in achieving better clustering
    and high-quality cluster labels (this is especially true when clustering
    smaller content, such as search results). Linguistic preprocessing includes
    the following components and resources:
  </para>
  
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>stemmer</term>
      <listitem><para>Stemming is the act of folding grammatical variations
      of words into their <quote>base</quote> forms. In English, for example,
      stemming transforms plural word forms into singular ones. For highly
      inflectional languages, such as Central European languages, 
      stemming may be the key to achieve good clustering results. &C2;
      uses a built-in set of stemmers from the Snowball, Lucene and
      Morfologik projects.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>stop words</term>
      <listitem><para>Stop words (or common words) include terms that
      are meaningless in the language. They are typically function
      words (<quote>is</quote>, <quote>that</quote>, in English) or
      words that are common in the analyzed body of text and should
      be marked as ignored. A good set of stop words helps the clustering
      algorithm in identifying <quote>gaps</quote> between other 
      phrases that can become valuable cluster labels.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>stop labels</term>
      <listitem><para>When clustering domain-specific texts, it is often
      desirable to filter out certain frequently occurring expressions
      that should not be considered clusters (<quote>home page</quote>
      for example). This resource provides means of avoiding such cluster labels.
      </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
    &C2; comes with a set of default lexical resources which may be used
    as a starting point for further tuning. It is recommended to gradually
    build a set of customized lexical resources that matches the specific content
    being clustered (for example legal documents will have a different set of stop
    labels than a corpus of e-mails).
  </para>
  
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="lexical-resources-location.xml" /> 

  <section xml:id="section.lexical-resources.in-workbench">
    <title>Tuning lexical resources in &DCW;</title>
  
    <para>
      The easiest way to tune the lexical resources is to use the &DCW; which will allow
      observing the effect of the changes in real time. To tune the lexical resources in &DCW;:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Start &DCW; and run some query on which you'll be observing the results
          of your changes.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Go to the <filename>workspace/</filename> directory which is located in
          the directory to which you extracted &DCW;. Modify lexical resource files as
          needed and save the changes.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Open the <guilabel>Attributes</guilabel> view and use the view toolbar's
          <guiicon><inlinemediaobject><imageobject role="html"><imagedata format="PNG" fileref="img/icon-attribute-grouping.png" /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject></guiicon>
          button to group the attributes by semantics. In the <guilabel>Preprocessing</guilabel>
          section, make sure the <guilabel>Processing language</guilabel> is correctly set and
          check the <guilabel>Reload resources</guilabel> checkbox. Doing the latter
          will let you to see the updated clustering results without restarting &DCW;
          every time you save the changed lexical resource files.
        </para>
    
        <figure xml:id="figure.preprocessing-attributes">
          <title>Preprocessing attributes section</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="img/workbench-preprocessing-attributes.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>  
        </figure>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>
          To re-run clustering after
          you've saved changes to the lexical resource files, choose the
          <guilabel>Restart Processing</guilabel> option from the <guilabel>Search</guilabel>
          menu, or press <guilabel>Ctrl+R</guilabel> (<guilabel>Command+R</guilabel> on Mac OS).
        </para>
        
        <figure xml:id="figure.workbench-restart-clustering">
          <title>&DCW; restart clustering button</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="img/workbench-restart-clustering.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>  
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="section.lexical-resources.stopword-files">
    <title>Stop word files</title>

    <para>
      Stop word files are UTF-8 encoded plain text files with a single word 
      in each line. Lines starting with <literal>#</literal> are omitted
      (considered to be comments). Files must follow a naming convention and be
      named <filename>stopwords.lang</filename>, where <varname>lang</varname>
      is a two-letter language suffix defined in <classname>LanguageCode</classname>
      class.
    </para>

    <example xml:id="example.sample-stopword-file">
      <title>A sample stop word file for English: <filename>stopwords.en</filename></title>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[# stop word file for English
ain't
thanks
need
needs
needed
vs
hit]]></programlisting>
    </example>

    <important>
      <para>
        Note that although words provided in the stop word file will be
        handled in a case-insensitive manner, they will otherwise be
        taken literally, that is no further processing, such as stemming will be
        applied. As a result, in order to declare that all
        <emphasis>have</emphasis>, <emphasis>has</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>having</emphasis> are function words, three entries
        corresponding to these words are required.
      </para>
    </important>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="section.lexical-resources.stoplabel-files">
    <title>Label filtering files</title>

    <para>
      The Lingo clustering algorithm, in addition to <link linkend="section.lexical-resources.stopword-files">stop 
      words editing</link>, offers more precise control over cluster labels by means of "stop
      label" regular expressions. If a cluster's label matches one of the
      stop labels, the label will not appear on the list of clusters
      produced by Lingo.    
    </para>

    <para>
      Label filtering files are UTF-8 encoded plain text files with a single 
      regular expression pattern in each line. Lines starting with <literal>#</literal> are omitted
      (considered to be comments). Files must follow a naming convention and be
      named <filename>stoplabels.lang</filename>, where <varname>lang</varname>
      is a two-letter language suffix defined in <classname>LanguageCode</classname>
      class.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Each line of a stop labels file corresponds to one stop label and is a 
      <link xlink:href="https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/regex/Pattern.html">Java regular
      expression</link>. Please note that in order to be removed, a label 
      <emphasis>as a whole</emphasis> must match at least one of the stop label 
      expressions. A number of example stop label expressions are shown below.
    </para>

    <example xml:id="example.sample-stoplabel-file">
      <title>A sample stop label file for English: <filename>stoplabels.en</filename></title>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[# stop label patterns for English
(?i)new
(?i)information (about|on).*
(?i)(index|list) of.*
(?i)(information|list|skip|join|cheap|access(es)?|corp(oration)?s?)
(?i).*(page|part|copyright) \d+.*
(?i)(official|offer(ing)?s?|lists|uses?).*
(?i).*(known|information|offer(ing)?s?|a range)]]></programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>
      All stop labels shown above start with the <tag>(?i)</tag> prefix, which enables 
      case-insensitive matching for them. The stop label in the first line suppresses 
      labels consisting solely of the word <emphasis>new</emphasis>. 
      The stop label in the second line removes labels that start in <emphasis>information about</emphasis>
      or <emphasis>information on</emphasis>, and the stop label in the third line removes
      labels that start with <emphasis>index of</emphasis> or <emphasis>list of</emphasis>. 
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
