<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN"
                 "http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % local SYSTEM "local-entities.ent">
  <!ENTITY % custom SYSTEM "custom-entities.ent">
  %local;
  %custom;
]>
<simplesect>
  <para>
    As a rule of thumb, the more documents you put on input and the longer the documents
    are, the larger clustering times. Interestingly, in many cases short document
    excerpts (such as contextual snippets for search results, title and abstracts or first 
    couple sentences of non-search results) may work just as well or even better than 
    full documents. Hence the first two most important performance tuning tips:
  </para>
  
  <formalpara>
    <title>Reduce the size of the input documents</title>
    
    <para>
      You can achieve this in a few ways:
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Rather than full text of documents, use their titles and abstracts, if available.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In case of search results, use the contextual snippet rather than the full
            document text. Not only will this improve clustering performance, but it
            will very likely increase the quality of clusters as well because you will 
            be clustering specifically the fragments the users asked for in their query. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you don't have document abstracts, but have access to some automatically
            generated summaries, use them. Otherwise, try clustering the title
            and the first few sentences of each document.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In certain cases, you may get decent clustering results with document titles 
            only, this variant is worth trying too.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </formalpara>

  
  <formalpara>
    <title>Reduce the number of input documents</title>
    
    <para>
      While removing large part of the input document set may not always be an option, 
      in many cases dividing the input into two or more batches, clustering separately 
      and then merging based on cluster label text may give reasonable results. The
      downside of this approach is that very small clusters containing just a few 
      documents are likely to be lost during this process.
    </para>
  </formalpara>
</simplesect>
